What we want to talk about now is running the pattern called the out route.
The out route can be very effective.
It's not a route you'll run to pick up a lot of yardage.
If you have a defensive back that really cheats to the inside you want to try to run the outside route.
This is also a good route to use if you're trying to save time and trying to pick up yardage and stop the clock.
You can through him to the outside and get out of bounds to stop the clock.
This is what an out route looks like (video demo).
We're going to have our receiver run about 5 yards and get the defensive back in his back peddle.
Then he's going to stop the route.
He's either going to give an inside jab step or a shank move and he's going to go to the outside, he'll open his body up, looking back, keeping the defensive back on the inside and he'll get the pass to the outside.
One important thing is when he catches the ball on the out route; he has to catch it, tuck it, turn and try to get up field as quick as possible if he has the defensive back.
A lot of times you'll see the defensive back try to cheat it from the inside.
If he can make the catch and head up field he's going to have a guy on his back and that's a very effective route.
That's how to run the out route.